"The Best Type of Sunscreen to Use"
What kind of sunscreen
should you use?
Cream-based is preferable
to spray-on,
since the completeness
of application
is more readily visualized.
To help with adequate coverage,
spray-on sunscreens should be
rubbed on immediately
after spraying.
Aerosolized sunscreens
are flammable
and can combust on skin
upon exposure to an open flame,
even after the sunscreen
has dried.
What's more,
the safety of breathing in
aerosolized sunscreen chemicals
has not been
adequately studied,
though frankly the same thing
could be said
about rubbing them
on your skin.
The concerns
surrounding sunscreen safety
are three-fold:
increased
intentional sun exposure,
vitamin D deficiency,
and untoward effects
from systemic absorption
of sunscreen chemicals.
In the 1800s, we first learned
that UVB caused sunburns
and formulated sunscreens
to block it.
Nearly a century later,
we learned
about the contribution of UVA.
Now, a full century later,
we are realizing that infrared
and visible light
may also be contributing
to cancer
and premature skin aging.
Sunlight comes to us
in three major bands:
visible light, ultraviolet,
and infrared.
Visible light includes
the colors of the rainbow—
red, orange, yellow, green,
blue, indigo, and violet,
or ROYGBIV.
Ultraviolet—UV—is to the right
of violet in ROYGBIV,
and infrared
to the left of red.
Sunscreen can protect us
against the free radical damage
of UV,
but half
of the free radical formation
in our skin from the sun
may be from the visible
or infrared spectrums,
which sunscreens
may not adequately cover.
So, that's where sun avoidance
strategies come in,
but you can imagine
how shade-seeking
could be undermined
by the solacement
of a sunscreen
security blanket.
What about vitamin D?
The theoretical concern
about sunscreen
affecting vitamin D status
does not seem to manifest
in the real world,
likely because
the UV dose necessary
for vitamin D production
is so low,
well before skin
turns a pinker shade.
However, concerns
about the systemic absorption
of sunscreen chemicals
were underscored
by the recent FDA bombshell
that not a single one
of sunscreen chemicals
in current use
can be considered
generally recognized as safe.
Only two active ingredients
got the green light,
the two non-chemical
"mineral" sunscreens:
titanium dioxide
and zinc oxide.
The revelation was based
on a growing body of evidence
that transdermal, meaning
through-the-skin, absorption
of sunscreen chemicals
was greater than
we previously thought,
raising unevaluated
safety concerns.
Unevaluated, because we
previously didn't think so much
got into our bloodstreams.
In 2019, a study published
in the Journal of
the American Medical Association
found that under maximum
usage conditions
over a period of days,
the blood levels
of all the sunscreen chemicals
they tested
exceeded the FDA threshold
that could potentially waive
further safety testing.
Then, in 2020, they found
that just a single application
of all the chemical sunscreens
they tested
surpassed the threshold.
Now, just because they're
absorbed into our system,
doesn't necessarily mean
they're unsafe.
It just means they need
to be tested for safety,
which, the FDA determined,
the multibillion-dollar
sunscreen industry
has so far failed to do.
The FDA concluded
that two ingredients
can be considered safe—
zinc oxide
and titanium dioxide,
and two can be
considered unsafe—
P.A.B.A.
and trolamine salicylate.
And the other 12 ingredients
that are currently marketed
have yet to be
sufficiently safety tested.
According to a review of more
than 700 sunscreen brands,
it appears P.A.B.A.
and trolamine
are no longer being marketed
in sunscreens
sold in the United States,
but they still may be available
in other countries.
Until the data are in
on the rest
of the chemical sunscreens,
I would recommend sticking
to the two mineral sunscreens.
Historically, they've tended
to be thicker and whiter,
which could lead
to even more severe underdosing,
but newer
micronized formulations
with smaller
mineral particle sizes
tend to be less noticeable.
This is particularly an issue
for those with darker skin.
The average built-in SPF
of black skin
(also known in the medical
literature as "ethnic skin"
or "SOC," skin of color)
is about 13 naturally,
compared with only about three
for white skin.
Though there haven't been
any interventional studies
on sunscreen effectiveness
for skin cancer prevention
in people with dark skin,
SPF 13 is not considered
sufficient sun protection;
so, the American Academy
of Dermatology recommends
regular sunscreen use
with an SPF of 30 or higher
for people of all skin types.
Unfortunately,
only about 12 percent
of non-Hispanic Blacks
and 31 percent of Hispanics
report regularly using
sunscreen,
compared to about 44 percent
of non-Hispanic whites.
Despite this,
the incidence of melanoma,
the deadliest skin cancer,
is five times lower
in Hispanics compared to whites
and more than 25 times lower
among Blacks.
However, the mortality rate
if you do get it
is higher among
African Americans,
presumed to be due
from delayed diagnosis.